This is ע"ב, Ayin Bet, we actually are ahead a full עמוד
amud so we pick up on ע"ב Ayin Bet עמוד ב' Amud
Bet with the new משנה. Mishna. Now the משנה Mishna is still
somewhat in the theme of the father and the groom who in
partnership annul the vows, but it actually gets to a somewhat in
passing a very important central question which the גמרא Gemara is going
to open up and explore. And I should mention, if it wasn't
already obvious, that our פרק Perek in נדרים Nedarim does what a
lot of מסכתא Massechta do and a lot of פרקים Prokim do,
which is start with the more obscure הלכה Halacha which is maybe
more fascinating because it's all complicated, like what exactly is the nature
of the partnership between the father and the groom and who's the
עיקר, Ikar, the father's the עיקר, Ikar, the groom is the one
that's piggybacking, how is it working in combination and so on, as
opposed to doing the normal thing which would have been to like,
let me explain to you how הפרה Hafara takes place, let's explain
what the 24-hour period is, let's explain what הקמה Hakamah is, let's
explain this, no, no, no, all of that gets sort of addressed
along the way, I mean eventually we'll also address it more directly
as we start talking about the more obscure and in some ways
more interesting case if you already know all the other stuff. So
it's really just another proof that the גמרא Gemara and the משניות
Mishnayos were so organized for those already in the know, not as
a נדרים Nedarim for dummies. Right, so it's already for people who
are in the conversation and let's sort of talk about maybe some
of the more obscure interesting cases first. Anyway, but this משנה Mishna
will help us get to a central question. So let's take a
look at this משנה, Mishna, the top of ע"ב Ayin Bet עמוד
ב'. Amud Bet. דרך תלמידי חכמים, Derech Talmidei Chachamim, it is the
way of תורה Torah sages, fascinating line in a
משנה, Mishna, דרך תלמידי חכמים. Derech Talmidei Chachamim. I'm even trying to
think when the משנה Mishna actually refers to תלמידי חכמים, Talmidei Chachamim,
תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim is obviously very common in the גמרא, Gemara,
right, but like when does a משנה Mishna directly refer to this
like as a class of
תלמידי חכמים? Talmidei Chachamim? Pretty easy enough to find out in one
minute on Bar Ilan. דרך תלמידי חכמים, Derech Talmidei Chachamim, it is
the way of תלמידי חכמים: Talmidei Chachamim: עד שלא הייתה בתו יוצאת
מאצלו, Ad shelo haysa bito yotzes me'etzlo, before a man's daughter was
going to get married and יוצאת yotzes here means נישואין. Nissu'in. Right,
remember conceptually קידושין, Kiddushin, אירוסין Erushin is not she's still in her
father's house. Leaving the father's house means נישואין. Nissu'in. So a man
had a daughter who was מקודשת, mekudeshes, before she was נשואה nesu'ah
he wanted to make sure to take care of all of her
נדרים. Nedarim. Right, because she made a vow prior to the נישואין.
Nissu'in. She made a vow either before קידושין, Kiddushin, after קידושין, Kiddushin,
but prior to נישואין. Nissu'in. What's going to happen once she becomes
a נשואה? nesu'ah? Can the father annul the vows at that point?
No, he's out of the picture. Can the groom, can the husband
annul the vows after she's a נשואה? nesu'ah? No, because it's קודמין.
kodmen. Right, so the only opportunity to annul vows that preceded נישואין
Nissu'in is to take care of it before נישואין. Nissu'in. Okay, so
here's his daughter, she's מקודשת, mekudeshes, before the חופה chuppah he should
take care of any possible outstanding vows. Okay, so דרך תלמידי חכמים,
Derech Talmidei Chachamim, עד שלא הייתה בתו יוצאת מאצלו, Ad shelo haysa
bito yotzes me'etzlo, before she would leave him, become a נשואה, nesu'ah,
אומר לה, omer lah, he would say to her, כל נדרים שנדרת
בתוך ביתי הרי הם מפורים, Kol nedarim she-nadart betoch beisi harei hein
mefurim, any vows that you've taken in my house they're annulled. So
give like a blanket annulment, sort of like call sort of like
what we do like at the התרת נדרים Hataras Nedarim on ערב
ראש השנה. Erev Rosh Hashana. Okay, I don't know what those vows
are, you haven't told them to me, obviously he hasn't told them
to him because if he told them to him the clock would
have run out already. Right, so it sounds like he doesn't know
what they are but he just says in case there are any
vows that you have made that I don't know about or whatever,
I'm annulling them now while I still have a chance. וכן הבעל,
Vechain haba'al, and also the groom, עד שלא תיכנס לרשותו, ad shelo
tikanes lirshuso, now you need the groom to be part of this
process, right, because he also once she's already מקודשת mekudeshes you need
his annulment as well. So also he wants to take care of
it before the נישואין, Nissu'in, right, because after the נישואין Nissu'in if
it's קודמין kodmen the father's out of the picture and it's prior
to his. The only reason he can do it now is because
it was still fundamentally the father, but you need his participation. So
the groom as well before the נישואין, Nissu'in, אומר לה, omer lah,
will say, כל נדרים שנדרת עד שלא תיכנסי לרשותי הרי הם מופרים,
Kol nedarim she-nadart ad shelo tikanesi lirshusi harei hein mufarim, any vows
you might have taken before the
חופה, chuppah, they are annulled. שמשתיכנס לרשותו, She-mishetikanes lirshuso, once there's a
חופה, chuppah, אינו יכול להפר, eino yachol lehafer, he can no longer
do it because they're קודמין. kodmen. So basically we've got that this
girl is only once she's נשואה nesu'ah there's no chance of addressing
earlier vows, so the father and the groom together give her a
blanket annulment, obviously quite clearly sounds like they haven't heard it, because
then you wouldn't need it to be framed in a blanket way
and because then it would have had to say that
the clock that's running out here, there's no clock that's running out
here, it's oh yeah they'll make sure to say it eventually or
whatever, it makes it clear that they have not heard it. Yes.
So I mean to me that seems like a pretty big חידוש
chiddush for a number of reasons because if I'm just thinking of
the פסוקים pesukim in מטות, Matos, מן היום שמעו, min hayom shema'o,
which sounds like... Excellent!
So that's the very first point the גמרא Gemara says.
But the other thing is, if you're already setting up this
model, then unless it becomes a bit cumbersome, but then presumably a
husband could just do that every night, right?
Meaning to his wife.
Exactly, exactly.
Exactly. So that's the question the גמרא Gemara asks. And as I
said, this משנה Mishna is just sort of telling us something else
in passing, you know, they better take care of it before it
gets to before she gets נשואין, nissuin, but it winds up telling
us something about the process of הפרה hafara and about this idea
of ביום שמעו. b'yom sham'o. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. בעא רמי בר חמא. Ba'i Rami Bar Chama. So רמי
בר חמא Rami Bar Chama asks. בעל מהו שיפר בלא
שמיעה?
Ba'al mahu
sheyafer belo shmiya? Can the husband—and it would be the same about
the father, we're not distinguishing, right—can the husband or the father annul
without having heard? ושמע אישה גביה הוא? V'shama isha gabeyhu? Does
the husband have to hear? Is that what's necessary to trigger his,
you know, give him the ability to do the annulment? או לאו
דווקא הוא? O lav davka hu? או לאו דווקא הוא? O lav
davka hu? It's so funny to take a פסוק pasuk from the
תורה Torah and you'll say, yeah, לאו דווקא. lav davka. Okay. לא
תעשה כל מלאכה. Lo ta'aseh kol melacha. לאו
דווקא. Lav davka. So
anyway, presumably what לאו דווקא lav davka here means is not that
we're just completely saying the phrase doesn't mean anything, but the phrase
would mean, I believe the following: He has twenty-four hours from the
time he heard. He doesn't have to hear to annul, but once
he's heard, he only has twenty-four hours to take care of it.
Not taking care of it within twenty-four hours of hearing is interpreted
as a הקמה. hakama. That makes a lot of sense. You heard
about it, you didn't object, right? So your non-objecting after hearing about
it for twenty-four hours, that is interpreted as הקמה. hakama. So it
wouldn't be לאו דווקא, lav davka, but it would be דווקא davka
in a particular way. You don't need ביום שמעו b'yom sham'o to
annul. The significance of ביום שמעו b'yom sham'o is that now you
only have twenty-four hours left. Okay. The גמרא Gemara doesn't say that,
but I think that's what you have to say is פשט. pshat.
We're not just סתם stam saying לאו דווקא. lav davka. Okay, yes.
Wait, wait, yeah, go ahead.
What about this, what's, hearing without hearing? Like written notification? I was
just going to ask.
Yeah, like written notification.
Oh, that's
an if you say ביום שמעו b'yom sham'o is דווקא, davka, then
maybe you could talk about what would constitute, but the גמרא Gemara
is saying that because as we pointed out, the משנה Mishna is
clear he does it with completely unaware, like there's no clock running
out. He says any vows you may have taken, right, so it's
clear that it's not just he didn't physically hear but he's unaware.
Okay,
so it's even a more of a לאו דווקא lav davka than
that. The לאו דווקא lav davka has to be as I said,
you don't need it to do the act of annulling, but its
relevance is that from the time you hear you only have twenty-four
hours left. Okay, so that's the question of the גמרא. Gemara. And
we're not going to go to like, okay, let's say someone can't
hear. It will go to that, yeah. In a way that you
have to hear her make the נדר, neder, not that he hears
later on that she made the נדר, neder, he has to hear
the נדר neder come out of her mouth. That's what the גמרא
Gemara says לאו דווקא. lav davka. First of all, again, that doesn't
fit the משנה, Mishna, right? The משנה's Mishna's case is that he
says, you came in after the משנה, Mishna, but the משנה's Mishna's
case is he says any vows you may have made are null.
So he didn't hear her do it, he doesn't know about it
until she made it, and it still sounds like he's annulling it.
So it sounds like the פשט pshat is he doesn't have to
hear anything. Okay, anyway, so that's the question. Does he have to
hear it at all or לאו דווקא? lav davka? No, as I
said, maybe it means that's when he has twenty-four hours, but basically
he doesn't have to hear in order to
annul. אמר רבא תא שמע. Amar Rava Ta Shma. Come and hear.
Our משנה. Mishna. דרך
תלמידי חכמים. Derech talmidei chachamim. It says it is that you know,
people who are—it's also fun that it says תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim
because maybe this is just somebody who's like conscientious, right, about
מדקדק בהלכה, medakdek b'halacha, right, careful that his daughter shouldn't, you know,
have a נדר neder that she's going to violate, etc. Maybe you
have to be a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham to know that you're
able to do this and it's not a problem that you didn't
hear about it. I don't know, but it is funny the identifying
of this category as תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. Anyway, the משנה Mishna
is דרך תלמידי חכמים עד שלא יצא בתו מאצלו derech talmidei chachamim
ad shelo yetze bito me'etzlo before his daughter goes ahead and gets
has the חופה. chuppah. אומר לה כל נדרים שנדרת בתוך ביתי הרי
הן מופרים. Omer lah kol nedarim shenadart betoch beiti harei hen mufarim.
Takes care of any possible existing vows. והא לא שמע? V'ha lo
shama? But he didn't hear it. So how does this work? So
the גמרא Gemara says, no. וכי שמע הוא דמיפר. V'chi shama hu
demifer. No, no, no. He means he's going to annul it when
he hears. He says, I want to annul any vows you might
have made. Okay, but they're not actually annulled now, what he's basically
saying is that he sort of opens up the conversation with her.
He says look, we gotta start a—we gotta annul any vows you
might have made until now. So if there are any vows I
want to annul them. And then hopefully she'll say oh yeah, actually
I did take a נדר, neder, and then he'll go—right. So it's
reading a lot into the משנה. Mishna. Okay. The משנה, Mishna, it's
reading it that he opens the conversation this way but he's actually
only going to annul it once he hears it.
That means that he actually—you're saying must has to go back and
annul once he hears.
Right. Now what you're thinking is going to be—wait one second, it's
going to come up, right. Maybe it should be חל לאחר זמן.
chal l'achar zman. We'll get to that. Okay. אם כן כי לא
שמע למה לי למימר? Im ken ki lo shama lama li lemimar?
So then why is he talking about it now if he hasn't
heard it yet and you need him to hear it in order
to annul it? So הא קמשמע לן אורחא דצורבא מרבנן. Ha kamashma
lan orcha detzurba merabanan.
It's teaching you that the way of a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
is להדורי lehadurei to like. it's going to come up, right? Maybe
it should be חל אחר זמן, chal achar zman, we'll get to
that. Okay. Who's דאמר: de-amar: אם כן דלא שמע למה ליה למימר?
im kein delo shama lamah leih lemeimar? So then why is he
talking about it now if he hasn't heard it yet and you
need him to hear it in order to know it? So, הא
קמשמע לן Ha kamashma lan אורחא דצורבא מרבנן, orcha detzurba merabanan, it's
teaching you that the way of a צורבא מרבנן tzurba merabanan is
להדורי lehadurei to go over back over it, meaning to open up
the conversation, to engage that possibility in order to get her to
say something. Very, very much פשט pshat in the משנה, mishnah, right?
He says, וכל הנדרים, vechol hanedarim, as a way of getting her
to articulate what she may, so that then he could annul it.
Okay, תא שמע ta shema מסיפא. miseifa. Fine, let's try the end.
וכן הבעל vechein habaal עד שלא תכנס לרשותו, ad shelo tikanes lereshuto,
but the husband before the חופה chuppah also says, אמר לה, amar
lah, the groom, אמר לה. amar lah. So you see he's doing
it before he heard. And it says הכא נמי, hacha nami, no,
here too, דאמר לה de-amar lah לכשאשמענה. lechishe'eshma'enah. He says to her
when I hear. Now there's a question here what the גרסא girsa
of the גמרא Gemara is or how to read the גמרא. Gemara.
Some have the גרסא girsa of the גמרא Gemara like we had
before. Not לכשאשמענה lechishe'eshma'enah but לכשאשמע lechishe'eshma והפרתי. veheifarti. אם כן im
kein blah blah blah and the exact same language as before, which
basically means he's opening the conversation to get her to say it
so that he could annul it. But just our גרסא girsa which
is just these two words, he says
when it takes effect, when he hears, without elaborating, when he hears,
that he will annul it. But he says it for when he
hears, means what I think Dov suspected, you
know, ראשונים rishonim interpret the way Dov was suspecting, which was right
now I am saying to her, I am annulling any vows and
this annulment will take place the moment I hear about them. Okay,
so which is a little funny, right? Because you would think that
if you need to hear, then you can't even do, not only
can the effect not take place now, but the act can't take
place until the act of annulment, right, can't take place. You know,
it's sort of like this debate about דבר שלא בא לעולם. davar
shelo ba le'olam. One example of דבר שלא בא לעולם davar shelo
ba le'olam according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is a man says
to a woman, הרי את מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li
once you get divorced from your husband.
Now that at least she's there, there's something holding her back or
whatever, you know, she's not in a position to accept קידושין. kiddushin.
But you could also say a non-Jew can say to a woman,
okay, הרי את מקודשת לי לכשאגייר. harei at mekudeshet li lechishe'agayeir. Okay,
now you would think, excuse me buddy, like before you're even Jewish
like we can't even talk about an act of קידושין, kiddushin, like
it's not just like some external problem that can't take effect right
now and could be, the effect could take place later. Like you
can't even get the act off the ground. Okay, what the גמרא
Gemara in order to deal with the משנה mishnah is coming into
like a middle position. Maybe you need to hear for it to
take effect, okay, it only takes effect once the בעל baal has
heard about it, but maybe he's empowered, maybe he's able to do
the act and get the ball rolling even before he's heard. It
just can't take effect until he's heard. Okay, that, you know, it's
an interesting middle position. We'll allow for the fact you need to
hear for it to take effect and we'll explain that the משנה
mishnah is you did it now for it to take effect later.
Now the ר"ן Ran says, so why didn't it say that by
the father? Why did it only say that by the husband? Right,
good question. So here's the difference. For the father, if he winds
up hearing later, the later might be after, after the חופה, chuppah,
right? That's what he's concerned about, it'll be too late, it'll be
after the חופה. chuppah. So then she's completely out of his control.
And since she's completely out of his control at that moment, right,
it's hard to imagine that the act he did before he heard,
when he wasn't able yet to annul, can now combine with the
hearing at the time when she's totally out of his control. Right,
neither one of those is a situation where he could actually like,
is in a position to annul and where he and so on,
so how could that actually work? By the husband it could be
different. By the husband he annuls now as an ארוס, arus, okay,
so he has a power to annul except he hasn't heard, so
that's preventing it from taking effect. And he'll hear it once he's
a בעל, baal, once she's נשואה, nisu'ah, when she's fully under his
control, and he, at least for נדרים, nedarim, it's true this annulment,
but at least for נדרים nedarim he's totally in a position to
annul them. So that maybe it's possible for it to combine, you
know, the act now with the effect later. So the father gets
around it by doing what again? The father has to open up
the conversation, hope she shares with him and then annul. He doesn't
get around it at all. The גמרא Gemara is reading the משנה
mishnah that if you have to hear, he basically has to get
her into a conversation, get her to share with him so that
he can annul before she marries. The groom is able to sort
of say I'm annulling now which will take effect when I hear.
And then even if he hears after the נשואין, nisu'in, it's okay
because that's an acceptable time, at least as a husband, for him
to do, to do the annulment. So it's not like any, it
could have been that either of them can, you know, get her
in a conversation? No, no, no, but the father can say like,
you know, when she's like three, all right, any נדרים nedarim for
the next eight and a half years? Oh, that's true. Based on
this read, the father could say like it'll take effect when I
hear as long as when he hears is while she's still under
his, in his בית, bayit, under his control. And a husband can
say like, you know, from the moment he marries her, all right,
any נדרים, nedarim, I'm, you know, any נדרים, nedarim, right, once there's
a נשואין, nisu'in, once there's a נשואין, nisu'in, you essentially say right,
any נדרים nedarim that you make, I'm annulling now and it'll take
effect the moment I hear about them. Of course he would have
to keep on saying that because that would only work for נדרים
nedarim that already existed, right? We're still, we're dealing with נדרים nedarim
that exist that you haven't heard about yet. A second A second
level question would be: Can you annul נדרים nedarim even before they
exist? Well that's what we hold on, we're gonna get there, hold
on, we're gonna get there. We haven't got there yet. Okay, so
we've raised the possibility that you can annul a vow that exists
before you've heard about it. That's certainly פשט pshat of the משנה,
mishnah, that it would actually take effect. Okay, in order to accommodate
though the משנה mishnah we said maybe not. Maybe the act of
annulling can be, and all of this is that the vow already
exists, the act of annulling can take effect before you've heard about
it, but the
effect of it would only be,
you know, would only be once you've heard about it. That's how
we're trying to make the משנה mishnah work with the fact that
you have to hear. Right, because that's how we're interpreting it as
the משנה. mishnah. Exactly. Let's so now we're going to keep on
going. Okay, תא שמע. ta shema. האומר לאשתו, ha-omer le-ishto, man says
to his wife, this is the משנה mishnah coming up: כל נדרים
שתדורי עד שאבוא ממקום פלוני. kol nedarim she-tidori ad she-avo mi-makom ploni.
You know, let's take a look at the משנה mishnah because it's
we'll see it in the full.
Turn to page ע"ה עמוד א'. Ayin Heh Amud Aleph.
All right, so האומר לאשתו, ha-omer le-ishto, guy
says to his wife, כל נדרים שתדורי מכאן עד שאבוא ממקום פלוני.
kol nedarim she-tidori mi-kan ad she-avo mi-makom ploni. Okay, I'm basically about
to leave on a business trip.
Any vows that you make as of now until I return, הרי
הן קיימין. harei hen kayamin. I'm being מקיים mekayem them. לא אמר
כלום. lo amar klum. That everybody agrees. You can't be מקיים mekayem
them.
Now these are vows that do not yet exist. Not only has
he not heard them, they don't exist yet. So you cannot be
מקיים mekayem
a vow that does not exist. Okay, however if he says הרי
הן מופרין, harei hen mofarin, I'm annulling them as of now, these
vows that don't exist, so רבי אליעזר אומר מופר, Rabbi Eliezer omer
mufar, it works. וחכמים אומרים אינו מופר, ve-chachamim omrim eino mufar, it
doesn't work. Now why does Rabbi Eliezer think you're more able to
annul it before it exists than to be מקיים mekayem it before
it exists? So אמר רבי אליעזר, amar Rabbi Eliezer, well because for
annulling it didn't exist yet either, anyway, so and now exactly. אמר
רבי אליעזר, amar Rabbi Eliezer, אם הפר נדרים שבאו לכלל איסור, לא
יפר נדרים שלא באו לכלל איסור? im hefer nedarim she-bau li-khlal issur,
lo yafer nedarim she-lo bau li-khlal issur? He says a נדר neder
before it exists is in even a better position to be annulled,
right? Because you're annulling it, you're getting rid of it. So if
you can get rid of something once it's there, you know, prevention
is an ounce of prevention is worth a pound of cure, right?
So if you can get rid of it once it's already present,
how much more so can you do הפרה hafarah to prevent it
from even coming into existing altogether?
Okay, it's a preventative measure.
And that's why he says it's different than קיום. kiyum. קיום kiyum
is strengthening it. You cannot strengthen it, right, until it's there. It
needs to be there for then you to strengthen. You can't strengthen
it if it doesn't exist yet. But to prevent it or to
get rid of it, so why, you're in a better position to
prevent it from even taking effect. You'd say that הפרה hafarah means
it has to
be there already. Well, okay, anyway, אמרו לו, amru lo, they said
back to him, הרי הוא
אומר, harei hu omer, no, the verse says אישה יקימנו ואישה יפירנו,
ishah yekimenu ve-ishah yefirenu, her husband will establish it and her husband
will annul it, כל שבא לכלל הקם בא לכלל הפר. kol she-ba
li-khlal hakam ba li-khlal hafer. Only something that can be established can
be annulled. לא בא לכלל הקם לא בא לכלל הפר lo ba
li-khlal hakam lo ba li-khlal hafer if it cannot be established or
it doesn't exist yet, it can't be annulled. Now it might just
be that that's how they understand the mechanism of annulment. You know,
it's just the mechanics work. Yes, conceptually it's easier to prevent something
than to get rid of it, but the mechanics work with something
that's existent. Or it could just be like גזירת הכתוב gezeirat ha-katuv
and technically you're right, that should be the logic, but the תורה
Torah says that they have to be in the same פרשה. parashah.
Well also you can say the opposite logic, right? Anything that you
can be מפר meifer you can be מקיים. mekayem. But Rabbi Eliezer
concedes that you can't be מקיים mekayem it before it exists.
That's that's his downfall, as it were, you know, but okay.
So here you have this fascinating debate, forget if you have heard
about it, you have the possibility, right, that you could be מפר
meifer it according to Rabbi Eliezer before it even exists. All right,
so to be מקיים mekayem it have to exist
and maybe you have to hear about it as well, etc. Although
no, like actually if you think about it according to that משנה,
mishnah, you don't have to hear about it to be no, no,
I'm sorry, what? Right, you can't be מקיים mekayem it, right. The
משנה mishnah says you can't be מקיים mekayem it if it doesn't
exist yet, right? Yeah, you can't be מקיים mekayem it if it
doesn't exist. Whether you need to hear about it, not clear. Anyway,
so the משנה mishnah says that you can't be מקיים mekayem it
if it doesn't exist, but according to Rabbi Eliezer you can be
מפר meifer it if it doesn't exist. So certainly you don't have
to hear about it according to Rabbi Eliezer. So let's take a
look. So הגמרא ha-gemara says like this: תא שמע, האומר לאשתו כל
נדרים שתדורי עד שאבוא ממקום פלוני הרי הן קיימין לא אמר כלום.
ta shema, ha-omer le-ishto kol nedarim she-tidori ad she-avo mi-makom ploni harei
hen kayamin lo amar klum. You're trying to מקיים mekayem something that
doesn't exist, you don't do anything because you can only strengthen something
once it's already there. It needs already have some strength to begin
with for you to fully anchor that strength. הרי הן מופרין, harei
hen mofarin, but if you try to be מפר meifer before it
exists, רבי אליעזר אומר מופר. Rabbi Eliezer omer mufar. He says it
does work and וחכמים ve-chachamim disagree. Fine, they disagree just because it
doesn't exist, but nobody says that there's a problem that you didn't
hear about it. The whole debate is can you be מפר meifer
before it exists. Nobody seems to be bothered about the fact that
you haven't heard about it. So הגמרא ha-gemara says והא לא שמע,
ve-ha lo shama, you didn't hear it and that doesn't seem to
bother either Rabbi Eliezer or וחכמים. ve-chachamim. So הגמרא ha-gemara says הכא
נמי דאמר לכשישמענא. hakha nami de-amar le-khi-ishmana. All right, so it'll be
a case where he says I am annulling it as of now
that... take effect when I hear about it. Okay, so again we're
doing the breaking up of the process, the act of annulling. They're
discussing the act of annulling, and that take, the act take place
before it exists or not, but אין הכי נמי in hachi nami
the effect of it will have to be will only take effect
once he actually hears about it. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, if that's true, ולמה לי v'lama li why does he have
to מיהשתא, mi-hashtah, why does he have to then make the statement
before he goes on his trip? לכשישמע יפר לה, lich'sheyishma yeifer la,
let him wait till he gets back. In our משנה Mishnah we
understand why you have to do it now, because otherwise like it
might be like too late, right? It'll be קודמין kodmin or whatever,
you need to do it before the נישואין. nisuin. But here, as
long as it's not going to take effect till later, let him
just take care of it when it becomes an issue later. So
the גמרא Gemara says כסבר דלמא מטרידא ההיא שעתא, kasvar dilma matreeda
ha-hee sha'ata, no, just coming back from my trip, I'll be trying
to get unpacked and take a nap or whatever and my wife's
going to tell me about some נדר neder she took and I'm
not going to pay attention, by the time I wake up whatever,
I'll have forgotten about it, it'll have been twenty-four hours, okay? So
that's why I want to take care of it now. Alright, so
basically again פשט pshat clearly of our משנה, Mishnah, of that משנה
Mishnah is you don't have to hear about it. But now what
the גמרא Gemara is saying is we can sort of say that
you only it'll only take effect you might not have to hear
about it to do the act of הפרה, hafara, that we can't
get out of, but maybe it'll only take effect once he actually
hears about it. Okay, and we've also now introduced the position of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says that you can actually do the
act of הפרה hafara at least the act even before it exists.
Alright, until she might be so over, you know, he was Correct,
that would be the נפקא מינה. nafka mina. Okay, תא שמע, ta
shma, come and hear. האומר לאפוטרופוס ha-omer l'apotropus this is also coming
up or whatever, כל נדרים שתדור אשתי מכאן עד שאבוא ממקום פלוני.
kol nedarim she-tidor ishti mikan ad she-avo mimakom ploni. He's going on
a trip and he decides I'm not going to just do it,
I'm going to let my friend take over that, okay? The guy
who's sort of in charge of running the house. I say to
him, well we're going to see, if you hear my wife take
any vow, הפר, hafer, go annul it, והפר לה, v'heifer la, and
he annulled it. יכול יהיו מופרים, yachol yihiyu mufarim, maybe they would
be annulled. תלמוד לומר אישה יקימנו ואישה יפירנו. talmud lomar isha yekimenu
v'isha yefirenu. No, no, no, it's got to be only the husband
can do it. It's not a
power that you can transfer.
דברי רבי יאשיה. divrei Rabbi Yoshiah. That's what רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiah
says.
אמר לו רבי יונתן, amar lo Rabbi Yonatan, רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonatan
said to him, מצינו בכל התורה כולה שלוחו של אדם כמותו. matzinu
be-chol ha-Torah kulo shlucho shel adam k'moto. Every why not? Why can't
you have a שליח shaliach here to do it? Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says here's an interesting debate about whether this is a
power that can be transferred, right? Normally you can make a שליח.
shaliach. There are some powers that can't be transferred. There are some
things the way like the רב חיים Reb Chaim and the בריסקרס
Briskers like conceptually sort of try to frame it, it's like there's
some things that are about you physically doing it, not about you
being empowered. First of all, you can't make somebody a שליח shaliach
to do a מצוה. mitzvah. But also, let's talk about even a
legal act, חליצה. chalitzah. You can't make somebody to be a שליח
shaliach to do חליצה, chalitzah, right? חליצה chalitzah is about actually personally
physically participating in the act. The way actually that that you know
the עסק דחליצה eisek d'chalitzah somehow is framed in this Brisker approach
is that you're not the one that is freeing your wife, actually
you know she's not the one that's let's say freeing herself from
you, she's the one that's a little bit more active, right? It's
that the תורה Torah says if you go through the act, then
the תורה Torah sort of frees her. Okay, so it's not that
you now are empowered and you're the one. You do the act
and like the תורה Torah then releases or changes her status. So
anyways, it is important that even sometimes in legal acts it requires
the person, it's not seen as a power invested in the person
that can be transferred. Okay, so here this is the debate whether
the הפרה hafara is a power invested in the בעל ba'al that
can be transferred or not, or it has to be only the
husband. But now the גמרא Gemara says fine, ואפילו רבי יאשיה, v'afilu
Rabbi Yoshiah, even רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiah that says that it works,
says it doesn't work, לא קאמר אלא משום דגזירת הכתוב הוא אישה
יקימנו ואישה יפירנו, lo ka-amar ela mishum d'gzeirat hakatuv hu isha yekimenu
v'isha yefirenu, that you cannot transfer this power. אבל דכולי עלמא שלוחו
של אדם כמותו. aval d'chulei alma shlucho shel adam k'moto. Everybody would
agree that if it wasn't for that פסוק, pasuk, at least in
principle you could have transferred it to the שליח. shaliach. Now why
could you transfer it to the שליח? shaliach? והא לא שמיע ליה.
v'ha lo shmeia leh. The שליח shaliach didn't hear the vow, so
how does the שליח shaliach have the power to do it? It
seems like the שליח shaliach is, no, excuse me, not the שליח,
shaliach, you didn't hear the vow. The שליח shaliach might have heard
it. You didn't hear the vow. So if you didn't, right, the
שליח shaliach is there, you're on your trip, you say to your
שליח shaliach if you hear her make a vow annul it, so
he's hearing it but you're not hearing it. So how could your
שליח shaliach do it if you didn't hear it? Now the obvious
answer is I already gave it away, what's the obvious answer? The
שליח shaliach hears it. If in truth if I can transfer him
the power to annul, then why can't he also be the person
to hear for me? Okay, so here actually here anyways so the
it's very interesting because the way the ר"ן Ran seems to sort
of frame this is hearing is the circumstances under which you then
become empowered to annul, right? So I cannot transfer transfer the power
of annulling, but the act of hearing is not that I somehow
am empowered to hear, it's just circumstances, the circumstances of me hearing
empowers me to annul. So I can't, I can't make somebody my
שליח shaliach to have experienced those circumstances. Once those circumstances exist, now
I'm in a position, now I can transfer that power I now
have to the שליח, shaliach, okay? Another way of thinking about it
is that hearing is a very passive type of an act. It's
not- you're not doing a legal act by hearing, so you're not-
the act that you do, the legal act is the act of
annulment, the hearing is the circumstances. So again, what you can transfer
to the שליח shaliach is a certain legal power, but hearing is
not that legal power. So therefore, the גמרא Gemara assumes- that's quite
fascinating, let's read it inside the ר"ן Ran because it is fascinating
that the גמרא Gemara doesn't even bother unpacking that. So it says
והלא שמע ליה, V'halo shama lei, it's like six lines from the
bottom end of the line in the ר"ן, Ran, כלומר בעל, Klomar
ba'al, the בעל ba'al didn't hear. אלמא לא בעי שמיעה, Alma lo
bei shmiah, you don't need hearing. וכי תימא לעולם אימא לך דבעי
שמיעה. V'chi teima le'olam eima lach d'bei shmiah. ושאני הכא דאיכא שמיעה
דאפוטרופוס, V'shani hacha d'ika shmiah d'apotropos, the אפוטרופוס apotropos heard. וכיון דשלוחו
של אדם כמותו, V'keivan d'shlucho shel adam k'moto, and since he's like
him, הוה ליה כאילו שמע בעל, Hava lei k'ilu shama ba'al, it's
like the husband heard. תירץ בתוספות בשם רב יוסף ז"ל Tireitz be-Tosefot
be-sheim Rav Yosef z"l דלאו הכי, de-lav hachi, that's not true. דאי
איתא דבעי שמיעה, De-i ita d'bei shmiah, if it needed to be
heard, מי איכא מידי דבעל לא מצי מפר ושליח מצי משוה, mi
ika midi d'ba'al lo matzi meifer v'shaliach matzi meshaveh, that if it
needed to be heard, so he basically makes it not exactly what
I'm saying, but like a little bit more of a technical point.
If the שליח shaliach heard and the husband didn't hear, then the
husband isn't in a position to annul. The only person in a
position to annul is the שליח, shaliach, and then your שליח shaliach
can't have power that you don't have, so therefore that wouldn't work
because even though maybe the שליח shaliach did have the right circumstances,
he can't have the power if you don't have that power. Of
course you could say well, you know, maybe I do have the
power, if he heard it it's like I heard it, so now
I also have the power. Anyway, the simple explanation is, and I
think actually it's in the תוספות, Tosefot, is my גמרא Gemara does
not have a תוספות Tosefot in this פרק, perek, but some of
the newer גמרות Gemarot actually have a תוספות Tosefot that was added
on the bottom from a different manuscript. Yeah, let me see. I
think תוספות Tosefot there says a little bit more simply along the
lines that I was just saying about this issue. Hold on, let
me take a look. Yeah, he says it in one line. ואי
תאמר שמיעת שליח כשמיעתו, V'im tomar shmiat shaliach k'shmiato, ותירץ בקונטרס v'tireitz
ba-Kuntres quoting רש"י, Rashi, דענין שמיעה אינו נעשה שליח. de-inyan shmiah eino
na'aseh shaliach. Okay, דענין שמיעה אינו נעשה שליח. De-inyan shmiah eino na'aseh
shaliach. Doesn't explain why, but I think it's what I said. Hearing
is not a legal act. You can't make somebody to hear for
you. You can transfer a legal power, you cannot make them you
in order to hear. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara understands, it's a
very nice conceptual issues around שליח, shaliach, but the גמרא Gemara understands
how could you, so basically everybody agrees that if it wasn't for
the idea of אישה יקימנו, Isha Yekimenhu, in principle you could transfer
this power to this שליח. shaliach. But how could he be empowered
if you didn't hear and the power to annul only comes after
you the husband personally have heard? So it seems like you don't
need to hear in order to have the power to annul. Okay,
so once again another proof that you do not need to hear.
So the גמרא Gemara says, top of ע"ג עמוד א, Ayin Gimmel
Amud Aleph, הכא נמי דאמר לה לכי שמענא מפר לה. Hacha nami
d'amar lah lechi shamana meifer lah. So he says to her, all
right, he says I'm sorry, he says to the שליח, shaliach, when
I hear about it, then you know, then you should annul it.
So the גמרא Gemara says what? לכי שמע ליפר ליה הוא, Lechi
shama leifer lei hu, when he hears about it let him annul
it. Why does he have to make a שליח shaliach do it?
No, סבר דילמא מטרידנא, Savar dilma matridna, maybe again maybe I'll be
distracted or whatever. So now of course it's still funny like what's
the scenario? He comes home he heard about it he's distracted and
the other guy remembers to go ahead and annul it. So the
actual simple more simple explanation is, although it does not necessarily fit
so simply in the words of the גמרא, Gemara, but is like
what said before, that he's basically saying you annul it when you
hear it and it'll take effect when I hear. Okay, so I
can give same way I could annul something, remember the only way
the גמרא Gemara can accommodate all of the evidence that sounds like
you can annul before hearing is to say you can do the
act of annulling before hearing but the effect requires to have heard
about it. So if that's true I can transfer that power to
the שליח. shaliach. You do the act of annulling when you hear
about it, it'll take effect when I hear about it. Why don't
you do it yourself when you hear about it? I'll be distracted
at that time. So you'll have already set things in motion, you
annulled it when you heard about it, and as soon as I
hear about it, then everything will take care of itself. Okay? Very
similar to all the previous answers. So again all of the evidence
is that you can annul before you hear. The way the גמרא
Gemara accommodates all the evidence is to say you annulled now, you
the שליח shaliach whoever is annulling now, and it takes effect, but
at least we'll insist that it only take effect once you hear.
That we'll hold out for them. Maybe it only takes effect once
you hear and you want to start things in motion earlier because
you might be distracted at that later time. Okay. So בעי רמי
בר חמא. Ba'ei Rami Bar Chama. So we don't have an answer
to that. But now we're going to raise a second level question
which might implicitly address the first one. בעי רמי בר חמא. Ba'ei
Rami Bar Chama. So Rami Bar Chama asks question number two. חרש
מהו שיפר לאשתו? Cheresh mahu sheyafer le'ishto?
Can a deaf person annul for his wife? Assuming that you don't
have to hear in order to annul, because if you had to
hear then it would be a moot point. Again assuming that hearing
is literally hearing. Okay. So assuming you don't have to annul, hear,
but you have to at least be in a position where in
theory you could hear, a בר שמיעה. bar shemiah. A hearer is
a בר דעת. bar da'at. Yes. So it's a חרש cheresh that's
a מדבר ואינו שומע. medaber ve'eino shome'a. Right. So that's... yes, correct.
So אם תמצא לומר בעל מיפר בלא שמיעה, Im timtzei lomar ba'al
meifer belo shemiah, if you say that a husband can annul without
hearing, משום דבר שמיעה הוא, mishum debar shemiah hu, at least he's
in the category of hearing. אבל חרש דלאו בר שמיעה הוא, Aval
cheresh delav bar shemiah hu, a deaf person that's not in the
category of hearing, היינו דרבי זירא, hainu de'Rabbi Zeira, maybe he would
be more excluded based on the principle of Rabbi Zeira. דאמר
רבי זירא De'amar Rabbi Zeira כל הראוי לבילה אין בילה מעכבת בו
וכל שאינו ראוי לבילה בילה מעכבת בו. kol hara'ui lebila ein bila
me'akevet bo vechol she'eino ra'ui lebila bila me'akevet bo. Anything that is
fit to be mixed, you don't actually have to mix it. But
if it's not fit, then the mixing prevents it from being good.
This refers to a מנחה. mincha. If you bring a מנחה mincha
of sixty-one, I believe it is, סאה... se'ah... sixty סאה se'ah with
oil, then the תורה Torah says you have to be בולל המנחה,
bolel hamincha, right? So you have to mix the flour and the
oil. But if you didn't mix it, it's still good. Okay. Even
if you just have the flour and the oil separate. Rabbi Zeira
comes along and says that's only if it is of a size
that is mixable. Once it's so large that it's not mixable, don't
ask me why a little extra makes it not mixable, I don't
know, anyway once it's so large it's not considered to be mixable
then it's no good. It has to at least have the ability
to be mixed even if it doesn't have to actually be mixed
in practice. Now of course whenever this comes up, תוספות Tosafot says
how do you get to decide when it's enough to have the
potential and when you really need the thing itself? Like any תפילין
tefillin that's fit to be put on, I don't have to actually...
like when exactly do you say that? Right? When exactly do you
say that is not clear. What tells חז"ל Chazal that in this
מצוה mitzvah the thing doesn't actually technically have to be done, it
just has to be in the category of being able to be
done? So I don't know the answer to that. But nevertheless the
גמרא Gemara is saying if we're going to concede that you don't
need to hear and we're going to say ביום שמעו beyom sham'o
is לאו דוקא, lav davka, maybe at least what we'll leave ביום
שמעו beyom sham'o to be talking about, to be saying is, at
least you have to be in the... have to have the potential
of hearing. Okay. And maybe therefore a חרש cheresh would be no
good. That's the question. או דלמא ושמע אישה לאו מעכב? O dilma
veshama isha lav me'akev? No, בדיעבד bedieved you don't need ושמע אישה
veshama isha at all. It's not... we don't even just shrink it
down to the role of having the potential. You don't need it
at all.
What he's not considering though is maybe there's another way for her
to communicate.
Yeah, correct, correct. We're assuming שמיעה shemiah means שמיעה. shemiah. אמר רבא
Amar Rava says Rava, תא שמע. ta shema. ושמע אישה, Veshama isha,
we have a ברייתא. braita. The husband will hear. פרט לאשת חרש.
Prat le'eshet cheresh. The ברייתא braita says to exclude the wife of
a deaf person. So it's very explicit that that case is excluded.
שמע מינה. Shema mina. We now hear that, again hearing is funny
in this context, we hear that from here. Now the point is
a lot of ראשונים rishonim say, oh from this we can therefore
implicitly assume that if a person is hearing they don't have to
actually hear. Because since the ברייתא braita only bothers to exclude the
case of the חרש, cheresh, it sounds like if just the fact
that you didn't hear is itself not enough to be a problem,
it's only if you actually... it's only if somebody's actually fully out
of the category. And that's reinforced by number one that this is
a question that's built on the assumption that you don't have to
actually hear. And that all of the previous evidence very clearly, the
פשט pshat of all that stuff that we had on the previous
עמוד amud is that you don't actually have to hear to annul.
So it's actually quite fascinating, right? The תורה Torah says you hear
and you annul, and according to at least פשט pshat of everything
and the way most ראשונים פוסקים rishonim poskim you don't actually have
to hear. Like I said, I don't think it's so crazy because
you could read the תורה Torah to say from the time you
hear you only have twenty-four hours or then it's like you're מקיים
mekayeim it. But it's possible to annul without hearing. All right? But
what the גמרא Gemara does say is if the person's out of
the category and a חרש, cheresh, then he can't annul. Okay, so
now just one last question.
איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. They ask the question. בעל מהו שיפר
לשתי נשים בבת אחת? Ba'al mahu sheyafer lish'tei nashim bevhat achat?
Okay? Can he annul for his two wives together? He has two
vows of two of his wives on the same day and he
says מופר לכן. mufer lachem. Okay? So can he do that? Why?
Because we say אותה otah דוקא, davka, the same way we wanted
to know about ושמע אישה veshama isha was that דוקא, davka, so
it says יפר אותה, yafer otah, הפר אותה. heifer otah. it versus
vs. אותה. ota.
Now it is going to the vow, right? Isn't it?
What what what is the אותה ota mean?
He heard?
Or does it mean the vow?
ושמע אותה veshama ota
על נפשה יקום al nafsha yakum וניא אותה. veni ota.
Yeah, you're right.
Actually
it
says
יום שמעו yom shamo והחריש לה, vehechrish la, יום שמעו yom shamo
יניא אותה. yani ota.
But if her husband disallow her, והפר את נדרה. vehefer et nidrah.
Okay, but the אותה ota by יני, yani, the הפר hefer is
הנדרה hanidrah אשר אסרה על נפשה, asher asra al nafsha, right? Does
it say יפר? yafer? No, it says והפר יפר אותם vehefer yafer
otam אישה isha יום שמעו yom shamo והחריש לה vehechrish la וקמו
כל נדריה וכל איסר אשר אסרה
על נפשה יקום,
vekamu kol nedareha vechol issar
asher asra al
nafsha yakum, והפר יפר אותם vehefer yafer otam
אישה. isha.
So the הפרה hafarah goes on the נדר. neder. The יני אותה,
yani ota, which is to disallow, goes on her. Right, because here
it's in plural, והפר יפר אותם vehefer yafer otam אישה ביום שמעו.
isha beyom shamo.
So you can only have the plural going on the נדרים, nedarim,
כל נדריה וכל איסר אשר אסרה על נפשה, kol nedareha vechol issar
asher asra al nafsha, right? So it sounds like that in the
פסוקים pesukim the verb הפרה hafarah goes on the נדר. neder. You're
voiding, you know, the vow, whereas the יני אותה yani ota means
you're disallowing her. Okay, so anyway, so this is saying אותה ota
her דוקא davka or לא דוקא lav davka or not, or maybe
even if there are two wives? אמר רב עינא תא שמע. amar
rav aina ta shema. אין משקין שתי סוטות כאחת. ein mashkin shtei
sotot ke'achat.
You cannot have two סוטות, sotot, you know, of one man has
two wives he's suspecting of adultery,
or maybe two men but anyway, either way you can't do them
both. But let's say that case, you can't do them both at
the same time מפני שלבה גס בחברתה mipnei sheliba gas bachaverta because
she sees her fellow wife there that oh look, she doesn't have
a problem with drinking and nothing happened to her, nothing will happen
to me. She doesn't realize that her fellow wife is innocent and
she's guilty or something. Okay, so you don't want to you want
to you know you don't want to interrogate people you know together,
you want to have each process done separately. רבי יהודה אומר לא
מן השם הוא זה, rabbi yehuda omer lo min hashem hu zeh,
that's not the reason, אלא משום שנאמר והשקה אותה לבדה. ela mishum
shene'emar vehishka ota levada.
You should make her drink her by herself. So here too it
has to be by herself. Now that's according to רבי יהודה. rabbi
yehuda. What about according to the חכמים? chachamim? Right? So there's some
debate in the ראשונים, rishonim, maybe there is a debate of רבי
יהודה rabbi yehuda and the חכמים chachamim and we don't know the
answer, but it's a debate. Others want to say that maybe even
the תנא קמא tana kama here agrees that it's based on the
פסוק, pasuk, but he's just explaining the reason behind the פסוק, pasuk,
sort of like a רבי שמעון rabbi shimon who דורש טעמא דקרא.
doresh ta’ama dikra. Okay, so it's not exactly clear how the גמרא
gemara answers, but it seems like the last words in the גמרא
gemara is it has to be individual for the wife. All right,
should we end here? I guess we should end, yeah. Do you
want to? We could go, do you want to get a whole
דף daf ahead? Yeah,
let's get a דף daf ahead. Okay.
Wait, what about but so what do we פוסק pasken in the
end though about like doing it, you know?
So
most ראשונים rishonim assume that the פסק psak of the גמרא gemara
is that the husband doesn't have to hear in order to annul.
Yeah, but can he be מפר mefer a נדר neder
before it exists?
We'll see that when we get to that next משנה. mishna. Okay.
Let's go ahead, let's let's get a full דף daf ahead. בוגרת
ששהתה י"ב
חודש, bogeret sheshahata yud bet chodesh, we looked we saw this before.
A בוגרת bogeret who is and the way the גמרא gemara earlier
read it is or a woman who waited twelve months. Again, this
is a woman that was a מקודשת mekudeshet and now the point
is it's not yet נישואין, nisuin, but it's the time for נישואין.
nisuin. Okay, it's been twelve months. Or now she's a בוגרת bogeret
and therefore it's assumed that you're going to have the נישואין nisuin
like very soon after she becomes a בוגרת. bogeret. אלמנה almana or
she's a widow, so she's outside of her father's house and there
was a קידושין kidushin and it's a second marriage, so in those
cases of a second marriage you only assume a month between קידושין
kidushin and נישואין. nisuin. ל' יום, lamed yom, it's been thirty days.
So these are all different scenarios where it's the time for נישואין
nisuin but not נישואין nisuin yet. רבי אליעזר אומר הואיל ובעלה חייב
במזונותיה, rabbi eliezer omer ho'il uva'ala chayav bimzonoteha, since חז"ל chazal said
that now is the time since you should have נישואין nisuin now,
you the husband are now obligated to start paying for her food,
so you're יפר, yafer, you're enough as if you're נישואין nisuin that
he can annul by himself without the husband, without the father. Which
is very bizarre. דאורייתא de'oraita she's not נשואה, nesua, right? And this
is all going to be לקולא. lekula. How do they give him
that power to annul? Okay. חכמים אומרים אינו הפרה עד שתכנס לרשותו.
chachamim omrim einu hafarah ad shetikanes lirshuto. No, you've got to wait
till they're actually married for real. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. gemara. אמר רבא רבי אליעזר ומשנה ראשונה אמרו
דבר אחד. amar rava rabbi eliezer umishna rishona amru davar echad. רבי
אליעזר rabbi eliezer that says that it's like they're really fully married
is saying the same as the first משנה. mishna. דתנן, detnan, we
learn in כתובות, ketubot, נותנין לבתולה י"ב חודש לפרנס עצמה. notnin livtula
yud bet chodesh lefarnes atzma. You give a virgin twelve months to
prepare herself. Now you gotta wait till they're actually married for real.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
רבי אליעזר ומשנה ראשונה אמרו דבר אחד. Rabbi Eliezer u’Mishna Rishona amru
davar echad. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer as saying that it’s like they’re
really fully married is saying the same as the first משנה. Mishna.
דתנן, Ditnan, ותנינא בכתובות, u’tanina b’Ketuvos, נותנין לבתולה י"ב חודש לפרנס עצמה,
nosnin l’betula yod bet chodesh l’farnes atzma, you give a virgin twelve
months, meaning for her first wedding, to arrange her trousseau. הגיע י"ב
חודש לפני נישואין, Higia yod bet chodesh lifnei nissuin, the twelve months
have come and it’s she’s he’s not yet marrying her. So he
now has his responsibilities kick in. אוכלת משלו, Ocheles mishelo, he has
to pay the food bills. אוכלת בתרומה, Ocheles bitruma, not only financial
responsibilities, she can even eat תרומה truma if she’s a כהן, kohen,
even though normally a woman has to be נשואה nissua to a
כהן kohen to eat תרומה, truma, she can eat תרומה truma now.
So you understand it's somewhat analogous, right? Her ritual status also is
already seen as a נשואה. nissua. So you have in the משנה,
mishna, he can't, normally he shouldn't be allowed to annul the vows
unless she's a נשואה, nissua, but close enough. We'll let him, it's
like she's a נשואה. nissua. She shouldn't be able to eat תרומה
truma unless she's a נשואה, nissua, but it's the time, so we'll
consider it like she's a נשואה, nissua, we'll let her eat תרומה.
truma. Okay.
אבל היבם, Aval hayabam, that's when it's a normal husband. But if
it's the case about that the husband died and we're waiting for
the brother-in-law to do יבום, yibum, then אינו מאכיל בתרומה. eino ma’achil
bitruma. Then he is not like the guy who's in the process
of קידושין kiddushin and נישואין, nissuin, and he's not in a position
even if he's a כהן kohen to have her eat תרומה, truma,
even after like the twelve months. שהתה ששה חדשים בפני הבעל, Asta
shisha chodashim bifnei habaal, she was married to her husband for six
months and then he died, וששה חדשים בפני היבם, v’shisha chodashim bifnei
yabam, and now she waited another six months for the יבם, yabam,
או אפילו כולם בפני הבעל חסר יום אחד, o afilu kulam bifnei
habaal chasar yom echad, או כולם בפני היבם חסר יום אחד, o
kulam bifnei hayabam chasar yom echad, the first case is the
bigger חידוש, chidush, or she waited eleven months and twenty-nine days, you
know, for the נישואין nissuin and then her husband dropped dead and
now there's the brother-in-law, or the reverse, one day she waited after
קידושין kiddushin with her husband and now eleven months and twenty-nine days
with the brother-in-law, in all those cases they don't combine. אינה אוכלת
בתרומה. Eina ocheles bitruma. She cannot eat תרומה truma by virtue of
the fact that there's this brother-in-law waiting to do יבום. yibum. Now,
the פשט pshat of this משנה mishna is that if actually she
had been, got to that stage of fit for נישואין nissuin with
the husband, it had been twelve months, and קל וחומר kal v’chomer
if she was actually נשואה nissua to her husband and then he
died, that the יבם yabam would then continue in that role and
she would eat תרומה truma by virtue of the יבם, yabam, right?
It seems like פשט pshat of this is just that waiting for
the husband doesn't combine with waiting for the יבם. yabam. There's a
רש"י Rashi actually says this is not true, that no matter how
long she was with her husband, the יבם yabam never, she'd never
eat תרומה truma by virtue of the יבם, yabam, but רבנו תם
Rabbeinu Tam disagrees, he learns this גמרא gemara like the פשט. pshat.
Okay, so basically what have we said? When a woman is time
for her to be נשואה, nissua, whatever the case might be with
the brother-in-law and whether that's the same or not, what when it's
time for her to be נשואה nissua and it's been twelve months
or whatever, she's considered נשואה nissua not only for financial purposes but
even for איסור issur purposes, she can even eat תרומה. truma. So
that's very similar to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says that the
husband can do annulling of vows.
Okay, זו משנה ראשונה, zo mishna rishona, that was the first teacher.
בית דין
של אחריהם אמרו, Besin shel achareihem amru, but a later בית דין
besin said, אין האשה אוכלת בתרומה עד שתכנס לחופה. ein ha’isha ocheles
bitruma ad shetikanes lachupa. No, we're not going to give him that
ability her that ability to eat תרומה, truma, which is like an
איסור issur issue, until she's really a נשואה. nissua. So this seems
like the question, how much are we prepared to consider her to
be
a נשואה nissua for איסור issur purposes before she's actually a נשואה?
nissua? So that's a reasonable lining up of the two positions. So
the גמרא gemara says, אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye
said to him, דילמא לאו היא, dilma lav hi, maybe it's not
the same position. עד כאן לא אשמעינן משנה ראשונה אלא מיכל בתרומה
דרבנן. ad kan lo ashmian mishna rishona ela meichal bitruma d’rabbanan. The
משנה ראשונה mishna rishona only said she could eat תרומה truma which
is a רבנן rabbanan issue, אבל נדרים דאורייתא אימא לאו, aval nedarim
d’oraisa eima lo, would never have allowed the husband to annul the
vows. Now what do we mean that תרומה's truma a רבנן rabbanan
issue, right?
רבנן תרומה? Rabbanan truma?
So it could be a position that like תרומה בזמן הזה truma
bizman hazeh is דרבנן, d’rabbanan, right? There's some גמרות gemaras that say
based on the question about קדושת ארץ ישראל kedushas eretz yisrael that
all תרומה בזמן הזה truma bizman hazeh is דרבנן, d’rabbanan, but that's
not really פשט pshat of this גמרא. gemara. This גמרא gemara is
making a different point which is presumably based on another גמרא. gemara.
Another גמרא gemara says that מדאורייתא m’dioraisa even an ארוסה arusa can
eat תרומה. truma. The question is why can the wife of a
כהן kohen eat תרומה? truma? So there's two possible פסוקים pesukim to
look at. One is, what is
it, אנשי ביתו הם יאכלו בלחמו, anshei beiso heim yochlu belachmo, people
of his household, and she's part of his household. The other is
talking about an עבד, eved, קנין כספו הוא יאכל בלחמו, kinyan kaspo
hu yochal belachmo, his a thing that he purchased with his money.
So the question is which case does the wife fall into? If
you say ביתו, beiso, that means a נשואה, nissua, if you say
קנין כספו, kinyan kaspo, קידושין, kiddushin, that's an ארוסה. arusa. So the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually says it's ביתו beiso and even דאורייתא d’oraisa she
needs to be a נשואה. nissua. The בבלי Bavli says it's קנין
כספו kinyan kaspo and דאורייתא d’oraisa an ארוסה arusa can eat תרומה.
truma. So why did they say she had to be a נשואה?
nissua? You tell me. Because we don't, not
you, well... Can you think? She's a
non-Cohen, she's not from a Cohen family. The Cohen, her Cohen groom
is feeding her תרומה. Truma. What's she doing? She is going to
be sharing this with her family, which are not כהנים, Kohanim, because
she's still living in her father's house, right? So that's the most
simple reason. There's another reason also, which is maybe between now and
the נשואין, Nesuain, he'll discover something about her he didn't like and
it'll be a מקח טעות Mekach To'us and then retroactively she never
would have been married. Okay. But the more simple reason is just
she shouldn't go ahead and share it with members of her household.
So the only reason she can't eat is דרבנן. drabunon. So it's
not a big deal to say once it's the time of נשואין,
Nesuain, we'll treat you like a נשואה, Nesuah, right, and then, you
know, and then we'll be, and then you will be allowed to
eat. The ר"ן Ran even goes further. He says because if you
think about it, right, at this stage
where he is paying now for her food bill, well how would
that work? I don't know, some, well even if he's paying for
a bill but she could still share it. Anyway, but the point
is that right now it's all דרבנן. drabunon. So since it's all
דרבנן, drabunon, it's not so it's not wouldn't be so terrible to
say you deserve to be a נשואה Nesuah now, we're going to
let you eat.
מה שאין כן Ma she'ein kein נדרים.
Nedarim. How could נדרים Nedarim if she's not really a נשואה, Nesuah,
how could the husband annul the vows? So even according to the
משנה ראשונה Mishna Rishona that was only דרבנן, drabunon, that wouldn't explain
how he could annul the vows. Okay, now it's really raising the
question what is the position of רבי אליעזר? Rebbi Eliezer? How could
רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer say he annuls the vows? So let's read
the last line. ועד כאן לא שמעת ליה לרבי אליעזר אלא לגבי
נדרים. V'ad kan lo shum'as lei l'Rebbi Eliezer ela legabei Nedarim. And
even רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, maybe he would even say that she
can't eat תרומה. Truma. And even though she can't eat תרומה, Truma,
the husband could still annul the vows. Why should vows be better?
Because by נדרים Nedarim כדאמר פנחס משמיה דרבא, k'd'amar Pinchas mishmeih d'Rava,
because that would follow the position of רב פנחס משמיה דרבא. Rav
Pinchas mishmeih d'Rava. דאמר כל הנודרת על דעת בעלה היא נודרת. D'amar
kol hanoderes al da'as ba'alah hi noderes. That if a woman takes
a vow and she's already in this relationship with her husband, that
she is like that she's already a נשואה, Nesuah, right, so therefore
she basically means I'm only vowing assuming that he's going to be
okay with it. All right.
And that's in her mind that it's בתנאי b'tnai that he's okay
with it. All right, and that's why it works, but not that
she really
is הלכתית halachically considered
a נשואה. Nesuah. It's circumstances
that affect
her psychological state. אבל תרומה אפילו מדרבנן נמי
לא אכלה.
Aval
Truma
afilu
m'drabunon
nami
lo
achla.
But
by תרומה, Truma, maybe from a formal perspective he's saying
I don't consider her a נשואה. Nesuah. I'm not going to let
her eat תרומה. Truma.
But what I will say is because of the relationship now she's
got with her husband and she's already been twelve months and it's
time to get married and he's providing for her whatever, she's now
thinking about being married to this guy and she has him in
mind when it comes to the issue of, it's like an implicit
תנאי tnai when it comes to the issue of, but not before
twelve months. Then it's a distant thing. It's not like she sees
herself in that relationship. Now that is a pretty weak answer you
know because technically because then like...
Yeah, I mean it basically means that he's not... the ר"ן Ran
asks the following question. The ר"ן Ran says, so if I say
I am taking a vow על דעת al da'as Dov there, or
Seth for that matter so we don't get confused with Dov's. So
does that mean that Seth can now say I like I'm מפר
meifer it, I don't want it even if I don't explicitly say
בתנאי b'tnai that Seth is okay. I just say like על דעת
al da'as Dov, I'm thinking about you know or Seth he says
to me while I'm making this vow. Does that mean he can
annul it or let's ask another question. If it's על דעת בעלה
היא נודרת, al da'as ba'alah hi noderes, can the husband now be
מפר meifer more than twenty-four hours later? Right? Does, so I mean
do the mechanics play in? So the you know, so the ר"ן
Ran has a very interesting answer to this. Take a look at
the ר"ן. Ran. He says like this. He says ואיכא דילפי מהכא,
v'ika d'yalpi mehacha, ואיכא דילפי מהכא, v'ika d'yalpi mehacha, סמכו להן מהכא,
somchu lahen mehacha, דמי שנודר על דעת חבירו הרי זה יכול להתיר
נדרו שלא על פי חכם דכי היכי דאמרינן הכא דמשום הכי מצי
בעל לחודיה להפיר משום דנדרה על דעתו ומפרש נמי על דעת חבירו
מצי מפר ולא גרע מפרש מחבירו, d'mi shenoder al da'as chaveiro harei
zeh yachol l'hatir nidro shelo al pi chacham d'chi heichi d'amrinan hacha
d'mishum hachi matzi ba'al l'chudeih l'hafir mishum d'nadra al da'ato u'mefareish nami
al da'as chaveiro matzi meifer v'lo gara mefareish mechavero, if you explicitly
say it's על דעת חבירו, al da'as chaveiro, מסתמא דבעל, mistama d'ba'al,
then implicitly on the דעת da'as of the husband. דהיינו טעמא הכא,
D'hainu ta'ama hacha, assuming we פסקן pasken like רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer,
which is funny because actually the חכמים Chachamim reject רבי אליעזר, Rebbi
Eliezer, right, and they say the husband can't, the guy can't be
מפר, meifer, but at least within רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. דהתם משום
דכנדר על תנאי דמי. D'hasam mishum d'cheneder al tnai dami. Okay, so
that's what some say. That at least within רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer,
if you say I'm doing it על דעת al da'as somebody else,
then they're like the husband and they can annul it. Okay. וזו
היא שגגת הוראה. V'zu hi shegagas hora'ah. This is like a real
error in פסק. psak. דהאע"ג דאמר דעל דעת בעלה היא נודרת אפילו
הכי צריך הבעל שיפר לה באותו לשון שקצבה לו תורה. D'ha'af al
gav d'amar d'al da'as ba'alah hi noderes afilu hachi tzarich haba'al sheyafer
lah b'oso lashon shekatzvah lo Torah. Right? You have to do a
formal act of הפרה. hafarah. You can't just say oh well I
don't like it, I don't agree. וגזירת הכתוב הוא, u-gezeirat ha-katuv hu,
ומשום הכי אין כל הלשונות שווין בו. u-mishum hachi ein kol ha-leshonot
shavin bo. You need as the right type of language, we're going
to get to this, we raised this question before, is there a
formal act, what's the language, וכדאמר לקמן. u-che-de-amar lekaman. ואי אמרת דבנודרת
על דעת חברו נמי אידך מצי מיפר משום דכנדר על תנאי דמי,
ve-i amart de-bi-noderet al da'at chaveiro nami idach matzi meifer mishum de-ki-neder
al tenai dami, if all it is is like an implicit stipulation
and a תנאי, tnai, הרי הפרתו של בעל ואחר ראוי שתהא נאמרת
בכל לשון, harei hafarato shel ba'al ve-acher ra'uy she-te-hei ne'emeret be-chol lashon,
then why would you have to do a formal לשון lashon of
הפרה? hafarah? And I would say is the question I would say
also like, you know what, presumably he has only 24 hours, right?
It presumably follows the same patterns of הפרה, hafarah, it's not like
you can do it any time. אלא ודאי רב פנחס הכי קאמר,
ela vadai Rav Pinchas hachi ka-amar, מיהי הפרה דבעל גזירת הכתוב הוא,
mi-hi hafarah de-ba'al gezeirat ha-katuv hu, it's a גזירת הכתוב gezeirat ha-katuv
that the Torah empowered him and it has formal rules. ומיהו משום
הכי זכתה תורה לבעל בהפרת נדריה. u-mihu mishum hachi zachata Torah le-ba'al
be-hafarat nedareha. Here's the reason, it's a formal mechanism, it's not just
a תנאי tnai or whatever, the הפרה hafarah is a formal mechanism,
got 24 hours, formal language, etc. But here's the person why is
it the בעל ba'al that's the one empowered with this ability? משום
דעל דעת בעל היא נודרת, mishum de-al da'at ba'al hi noderet, because
it's like a real amazing דרשינן טעמא דקרא. darshinan ta'ama de-kra. Why
did the Torah invest the husband? So you know, actually this is
not what I would have said at פשט pshat at all. It's
very empowering to the woman, I mean empowering or whatever, switches the,
switches it. It's not invest the husband cause hey buddy you're in
my house and therefore I, what I get to say goes, right?
That's I think how normally you would understand like why you know
he's the guy who's in control you can't do anything against his
will. No, it's reversing it. The reason the Torah empowers the husband
is a presumption that the wife would only do it if the
husband would agree. But it makes it about her, her דעת. da'at.
הילכך, hilkach, that's how we're interpreting what's going on in the פסוק,
pasuk, why the husband is invested. הילכך hilkach with that power, כל
שהיא נודרת על דעתו, kol she-hi noderet al da'ato, if anybody would
fit that role, now presumably not a stranger, it would have to
be somebody that's in a pseudo-husband or an ארוס arus type of
a position, חלה הכא גזירת הכתוב דאמר רחמנא. chala hacha gezeirat ha-katuv
de-amar rachmana. So we're expanding, what we're doing is we're actually דרשינן
טעמא דקרא darshinan ta'ama de-kra and we're saying when the Torah says
husband, בעל, ba'al, you know, אשה, ishah, husband includes even an ארוס
arus after twelve months when he is, when the relationship is effectively
the same and her דעת da'at is effectively the same as it
would be after נישואין. nisu'in. So it's a way that we redefine
what are the parameters, right, of that category of husband in the
Torah. אבל הנודר על דעת חברו דלא חזי ביה רחמנא מידי, aval
ha-nozer al da'at chaveiro de-lo chazi beih rachmana midi, but if it's
a guy that wasn't the husband at all, some סתם stam stranger,
okay, not an ארוס, arus, ודאי לא מצי מיפר. vadai lo matzi
meifer. Okay, but of course if you explicitly, if you explicitly make
a תנאי tnai you can explicitly make whatever תנאי tnai you want.
But this concept of על דעת, al da'at, it's a beautiful read
of the ר"ן. Ran. I mean, you know, it's really, you know,
we're going to go ahead and the Torah says husband, and רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says yeah, but husband doesn't have to be full
נישואין, nisu'in, it could be an ארוס arus who's in the position
that the relationship has gotten to the stage where it's the similar
dynamic as with a husband. And that's also in the Torah's category
of husband, right? It's very fascinating read of it, but you know
you, you know, חז"ל Chazal in a way do this all the
time. But you know it's really like, you know, it's really is
like, okay forget, you know it's not a complete rejection of the
formalisms. Anybody that, oh well I care for my sister as much
as my husband and I would only want it to be, no
no no no. It has to be somebody we can fit into
the husband category. This guy is an ארוס. arus. He could, right,
it's just that he's not yet נישואין nisu'in but it's close enough
that we could say it's like it's נישואין nisu'in and the Torah
would consider it to be a case of נישואין nisu'in by this
stage already because of the reasons that are relevant about this case.
Okay and that explains at least רבי אליעזר'ס Rabbi Eliezer's position of
why he can. Again the חכמים Chachamim disagree but that at least
explains רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.